<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document title="JRat with Apache Tomcat">


	<section-group>

		<p>
		I have received several emails from people having
		difficulty using JRat to monitor web application running
		within Apache Tomcat.  This document will attempt to clarify the a
		approach needed to monitoring a web application running in Tomcat.
		</p>

		<section title="Location of the JRat jar">
			<p>
			It is a common expectation that JRat will work if the jar
			<bold>shiftone-jrat.jar</bold>
			is added to the a webapps <bold>WEB-INF\lib</bold> directory.
			This is not the case.  The jar must be installed at the server
			"level" in Tomcat's <bold>common\lib</bold> directory.
			</p>
			<p>
			The symptom that most people will see if the jar is installed in the
			webapp, is that hey will be able to run the app without any problem.
			The problem arises when Tomcat is shut down using the
			<bold>shutdown</bold> script.  When this happens, output files don't get
			flushed correctly or written at all.  This problem does not occur if
			Tomcat is shutdown simply using Ctrl-C.
			</p>
			<p>
			The cause of this problem, is that when Tomcat is shutdown, it un-deploys
			all running webapps.  This means, that the class loader that contains the JRat
			jar, suddenly vanishes.  If one of the handlers attempts to load a JRat
			class, and they usually do, then it will fail.  This failure may be difficult to
			detect under Windows because the standard Tomcat start script doesn't pause
			before closing the console window.
			</p>
		</section>

		<section title="Configuring JRat Options">
			To add options to Tomcat's command line, the start scripts honor several
			environment variables; CATALINA_OPTS and JAVA_OPTS.  Either of these may be
			assigned to the following value.

			<code>-Djrat.factory=org.shiftone.jrat.provider.tree.TreeMethodHandlerFactory</code>
		</section>

		<section title="Output Files">
			Typically, Tomcat is started from the <bold>bin</bold> directory.  If this
			is the case then JRat will deposit it's output files in the directory
			<bold>bin\JRatOutput</bold>.  If you are starting Tomcat from a different
			directory (you will need to specify CATALINA_HOME) then the output
			directory will be created in whatever directory you are running Tomcat from.
		</section>


		<p>Send feedback to jrat@shiftone.org.</p>

	</section-group>



</document>